Hello, welcome to class everybody. My name is David Brown. This is a grammar class. Hello. Welcome. Welcome to class. Norma. Welcome. Hello. Thank you. How are you? I'm doing good. How are you? I'm doing great. Thank you.
مرحباً، أهلاً وسهلاً بالجميع في الدرس. اسمي ديفيد براون. هذا درس في قواعد اللغة. مرحباً. أهلاً بكم. أهلاً بكم في الدرس. نورما (Nūrmā)، أهلاً بكِ. مرحباً. شكراً لك. كيف حالك؟ أنا بخير. كيف حالك أنت؟ أنا بخير جداً. شكراً لك.
Norma, did you have a good weekend? Yes, I had* a good weekend with my family.
نورما، هل قضيتِ عطلة نهاية أسبوع جيدة؟ نعم، قضيتُ* عطلة نهاية أسبوع جيدة مع عائلتي.
Great. Excellent. Did you spend time with, you have a son, right? His name is Jose Pablo? Yes. He always tries* to play with me. So I can do anything at home about just playing with him.
عظيم. ممتاز. هل قضيتِ وقتاً مع، لديكِ ابن، أليس كذلك؟ اسمه خوسيه بابلو (Khūsīh Bāblū)؟ نعم. هو دائماً يحاول* أن يلعب معي. لذا لا أستطيع فعل أي شيء في المنزل سوى اللعب معه.
Okay, that does sound like a good weekend. In this lesson, Norma, we're going to talk about weekends and we'll talk about regular and irregular verbs, the difference between those two.
حسناً، يبدو ذلك حقاً عطلة نهاية أسبوع جيدة. في هذا الدرس يا نورما، سنتحدث عن عطلات نهاية الأسبوع وسنتحدث عن الأفعال المنتظمة والأفعال الشاذة، والفرق بينهما.
And how to describe our weekends using pronunciation and also sequence adverbs. Let's read these objectives here. Can you see the screen, okay? Yes, I can see it.
وكيف نصف عطلات نهاية أسبوعنا باستخدام النطق وكذلك ظروف الترتيب. دعنا نقرأ هذه الأهداف هنا. هل ترين الشاشة بوضوح؟ نعم، أستطيع رؤيتها.
Okay, great. Let's start by reading this part right here. Can you read this line for me? Talk about the past. You see all past verbs like washed, went, ate.
حسناً، عظيم. لنبدأ بقراءة هذا الجزء هنا. هل يمكنكِ قراءة هذا السطر لي؟ التحدث عن الماضي. ترين جميع أفعال الماضي مثل washed, went, ate.
to describe finished events. Okay. And the next one? And then the next order. Order your story. Use special words. First, then, next. After that, finally, to tell things in the right order.
لوصف الأحداث المنتهية. حسناً. والتالي؟ ثم الترتيب التالي. رتبي قصتك. استخدمي كلمات خاصة. First, then, next. After that, finally، لسرد الأشياء بالترتيب الصحيح.
Sound clear, practice saying -ed verb endings correctly. Okay. And write your story. Write a short paragraph, three to five sentences about a personal past event.
ليكن صوتك واضحاً، تدربي على نطق نهايات الأفعال المنتهية بـ -ed بشكل صحيح. حسناً. واكتبي قصتك. اكتبي فقرة قصيرة، من ثلاث إلى خمس جمل عن حدث شخصي ماضٍ.
Okay, great. So these are our goals for today's lesson.
حسناً، عظيم. إذاً هذه هي أهدافنا لدرس اليوم.
We see that we have the past, the present, and the future. We have different conjugations and many students struggle with the past tense quite a bit for two reasons: One, there are different ways to pronounce verbs that end in ED.
نرى أن لدينا الماضي والحاضر والمستقبل. لدينا تصريفات مختلفة والعديد من الطلاب يجدون صعوبة كبيرة في زمن الماضي لسببين: الأول، هناك طرق مختلفة لنطق الأفعال التي تنتهي بـ ED.
And also because there are so many irregular past tense verbs, probably more than 200 irregular past tense verbs that we need to memorize.
وأيضاً لأن هناك العديد من أفعال الماضي الشاذة، ربما أكثر من 200 فعل ماضٍ شاذ نحتاج إلى حفظها.
So we see that the basic verb structure is basically verb plus ed. And that's the simple past. And that works most of the time. So we just add ed to the end of it. For example, we have finished and in the past, it is finished.
لذا نرى أن بنية الفعل الأساسية هي بشكل أساسي الفعل + ed. وهذا هو الماضي البسيط. وهذا ينجح في معظم الأوقات. لذا نضيف فقط ed إلى نهايته. على سبيل المثال، لدينا finish وفي الماضي، تصبح finished.
A base verb, and then the rest. Here's an example here. Can you read this example for me?
فعل أساسي، ثم الباقي. إليكِ مثال هنا. هل يمكنكِ قراءة هذا المثال لي؟
Present, watch TV, past, yesterday, I watched* a movie.
الحاضر، watch TV، الماضي، yesterday, I watched* a movie.
Okay. Good. We're going to practice some pronunciation a little bit more. It could be difficult for native Spanish speakers to pronounce that ch sound in watched.
حسناً. جيد. سنتدرب على بعض النطق أكثر قليلاً. قد يكون من الصعب على الناطقين الأصليين بالإسبانية نطق صوت ch في watched.
But you'll get it. Don't worry.
لكنكِ ستتقنينه. لا تقلقي.
And so we see an example like this one, too. They play soccer. And then in the past becomes they played soccer. And you can hear a different pronunciation for this one.
وهكذا نرى مثالاً كهذا أيضاً. They play soccer. ثم في الماضي تصبح They played soccer. ويمكنكِ سماع نطق مختلف لهذا.
In the first one, a /t/ sound, the second one, a /d/ sound. And then here's another example. Can you read this one for me?
في الأول، صوت /t/، وفي الثاني، صوت /d/. ثم إليكِ مثال آخر. هل يمكنكِ قراءة هذا لي؟
She cooks dinner past she chicken dinner last night.
She cooks dinner الماضي she cooked dinner last night.
Great. So the basic spelling rules are that we need to add ed to the end of the verb.
عظيم. إذاً قواعد الإملاء الأساسية هي أننا نحتاج إلى إضافة ed إلى نهاية الفعل.
There are some times when we need to change the y to i and then add ed. For example, study becomes studied or cry,
هناك بعض الأحيان التي نحتاج فيها إلى تغيير y إلى i ثم إضافة ed. على سبيل المثال، study تصبح studied أو cry،
becomes cried  with i ed.
تصبح cried مع ied.
But most of the time, you'll just add -ed to the end of the verb to make it past tense.
ولكن في معظم الأحيان، ستضيفين فقط -ed إلى نهاية الفعل لجعله في صيغة الماضي.
All right. Let's continue. Do you have any questions for me before we continue on?
حسناً. لنستمر. هل لديكِ أي أسئلة لي قبل أن نستمر؟
No, I just want to, as you mentioned, it is difficult. This is one of the most difficult parts when I start learning English, the past tense because of that pronunciation part.
لا، فقط أردت أن أقول، كما ذكرتَ، الأمر صعب. هذا أحد أصعب الأجزاء عندما بدأت تعلم اللغة الإنجليزية، زمن الماضي بسبب جزء النطق ذاك.
But we try practicing and practicing.
لكننا نحاول التدرب مراراً وتكراراً.
I understand. And it's normal to feel a little bit nervous when we try to do difficult things.
أتفهم ذلك. ومن الطبيعي أن نشعر ببعض التوتر عندما نحاول القيام بأشياء صعبة.
So far, you're doing really, really good exceptional. So don't worry, Norma.
حتى الآن، أداؤكِ جيد جداً جداً، استثنائي. لذا لا تقلقي يا نورما.
All right. So one challenging thing, as you mentioned, is knowing all of these are regular verbs.
حسناً. إذاً أحد الأشياء الصعبة، كما ذكرتِ، هو معرفة كل هذه الأفعال الشاذة.
And so we need to memorize them. There really is no way around memorizing these different verbs.
لذا نحتاج إلى حفظها. لا يوجد حقاً مفر من حفظ هذه الأفعال المختلفة.
Of course, we need to use them in context, but we really need to memorize all of these irregular past tense verbs.
بالطبع، نحتاج إلى استخدامها في سياقها، لكننا حقاً بحاجة إلى حفظ كل هذه الأفعال الماضية الشاذة.
So we have some examples here. The past tense of go is went...the past tense of eat is ate.
لدينا بعض الأمثلة هنا. الماضي من go هو went... الماضي من eat هو ate.
The past tense of have is had* the past tense of see is saw past tense of drink is drank past tense of make is made.
الماضي من have هو had* الماضي من see هو saw، الماضي من drink هو drank، الماضي من make هو made.
Good pronunciation. The past tense of buy is what? Bought.
نطق جيد. الماضي من buy هو ماذا؟ Bought.
Oh, okay. And how about this one?
أوه، حسناً. وماذا عن هذا؟
Past tense of wake up is woke up.
الماضي من wake up هو woke up.
All right. And then we need to remember these conjugations for the verb to be.
حسناً. ثم نحتاج إلى تذكر هذه التصريفات للفعل to be.
So not only do we have a regular one, sometimes they look totally different in past tense conjugations.
لذا ليس لدينا فقط أفعال منتظمة، بل أحياناً تبدو مختلفة تماماً في تصريفات الماضي.
So we have be and then was or were for the word to be.
لذا لدينا be ثم was أو were للفعل to be.
All right. So these are just a small sample of irregular verb.
حسناً. هذه مجرد عينة صغيرة من الأفعال الشاذة.
I really recommend that when you have time, try to find lists of these irregular verbs and use them.
أوصي حقاً بأنه عندما يكون لديكِ وقت، حاولي إيجاد قوائم لهذه الأفعال الشاذة واستخدامها.
Think about them whenever you speak about the past. Make sure that you're conjugating them correctly.
فكري فيها كلما تحدثتِ عن الماضي. تأكدي من أنكِ تصرفينها بشكل صحيح.
Let's test a couple of these. And I think we can continue on because you're doing really well.
دعنا نختبر بعضاً منها. وأعتقد أننا يمكن أن نستمر لأنكِ تبدين أداءً جيداً حقاً.
The past tense of go is went the past tense of have is had the past tense of drink is drank.
الماضي من go هو went، الماضي من have هو had، الماضي من drink هو drank.
Good. The past tense of buy is... Bought?
جيد. الماضي من buy هو... Bought?
Wow. Okay. Your pronunciation really has improved a whole lot. I'm really impressed.
رائع. حسناً. نطقكِ تحسن كثيراً حقاً. أنا معجب جداً.
Thank you.
شكراً لك.
All right. So we have three different ways that we pronounce these verbs that end in -ed.
حسناً. إذاً لدينا ثلاث طرق مختلفة لنطق هذه الأفعال التي تنتهي بـ -ed.
And we've had some implicit practice with this before, but I think it's really useful to understand some of these rules too.
وقد تدربنا على هذا بشكل ضمني من قبل، لكنني أعتقد أنه من المفيد حقاً فهم بعض هذه القواعد أيضاً.
We have three different sounds that we make whenever we pronounce verbs that end in -ed.
لدينا ثلاثة أصوات مختلفة نصدرها عندما ننطق الأفعال التي تنتهي بـ -ed.
One is with a /t/sound here with your teeth.
أحدها هو صوت /t/ هنا بأسنانك.
The other one is with a /t/ sound and it's behind the teeth right there in the alveolar ridge, it's called.
والآخر هو صوت /t/ ويكون خلف الأسنان مباشرة هناك في الحافة السنخية (al-ḥāffah as-sinkhiyyah)، هكذا تسمى.
That's where we pronounce the d-d sound. And then we have the id sound.
هناك ننطق صوت /d/. ثم لدينا صوت /ɪd/.
So it starts with this vocal sound here is where vowels come from.
إذاً يبدأ هذا بالصوت الجهوري هنا حيث تأتي الحركات (أصوات العلة).
And then it ends with the dip sound in the roof of your mouth.
ثم ينتهي بصوت /d/ في سقف فمك.
So we have dip and id and it depends on the final consonant.
لذا لدينا /d/ و /ɪd/ ويعتمد ذلك على الحرف الساكن الأخير.
So the final consonant sound of watch, for example, is ch repeat repeat repeat.
إذاً الحرف الساكن الأخير في watch، على سبيل المثال، هو ch كرري كرري كرري.
There you go. Very good. All right. So we have watched? This one's very difficult.
هكذا. جيد جداً. حسناً. إذاً لدينا watched? هذا صعب جداً.
Watched? Watched? Watched? Watched? Very good.
Watched? Watched? Watched? Watched? جيد جداً.
Great. And look becomes. Look.
عظيم. و look تصبح. Looked.
Looks very good. Stop is. Stop. Right. So we don't have a sound that starts here with the a /t/ at the end.
Looks جيد جداً. Stop هي. Stopped. صحيح. إذاً ليس لدينا صوت يبدأ هنا بصوت /t/ المهموس في النهاية.
And then we have the d sound. Remember in the roof of the mouth.
ثم لدينا صوت /d/. تذكري في سقف الفم.
So we have play in the past becomes remember /d/. Repeat after me.
إذاً لدينا play وفي الماضي تصبح، تذكري /d/. كرري بعدي.
Very good. Played. Played.
جيد جداً. Played. Played.
Good. This one? Opened.
جيد. هذا؟ Opened.
Great. And this one?
عظيم. وهذا؟
Lived. Wow. Perfect. Awesome.
Lived. رائع. مثالي. مدهش.
So you can memorize these rules here.
إذاً يمكنكِ حفظ هذه القواعد هنا.
You can learn them after some time of just practicing and hearing them for a long time.
يمكنكِ تعلمها بعد بعض الوقت من مجرد التدرب عليها وسماعها لفترة طويلة.
But if you remember that if it starts or rather if the final consonant is L B and B G M R Z or J,
ولكن إذا تذكرتِ أنه إذا كان الحرف الساكن الأخير هو L, V, N, G, M, R, Z, أو J (الأصوات الجهورية)،
then it will result in that /d/ sound at the end.
فسينتج عن ذلك صوت /d/ في النهاية.
The most important rule to remember is that when the final consonant is "t" or "d",
أهم قاعدة يجب تذكرها هي أنه عندما يكون الحرف الساكن الأخير "t" أو "d"،
then we're going to pronounce the -id at the end.
فإننا سننطق /ɪd/ في النهاية.
So we have wanted in the final consonant is "t".
لذا لدينا wanted والحرف الساكن الأخير هو "t".
wanted it's wanted the final consonant of need is what? Needed.
wanted، إنها wanted. الحرف الساكن الأخير في need هو ماذا؟ Needed.
So it's D. The final consonant is D. So it's needed and decided.
إذاً هو D. الحرف الساكن الأخير هو D. لذا فهي needed و decided.
Decided. Perfect. All right. So we add an extra syllable with that id sound at the end.
Decided. مثالي. حسناً. إذاً نضيف مقطعاً إضافياً مع صوت /ɪd/ ذاك في النهاية.
I think we can continue on. How do you feel?
أعتقد أننا يمكن أن نستمر. كيف تشعرين؟
Does this seem easy to you or is it a little too difficult or what do you think?
هل يبدو هذا سهلاً لكِ أم أنه صعب قليلاً أم ماذا تعتقدين؟
I think you're doing great.
أعتقد أنكِ تبدين أداءً رائعاً.
No, I feel comfortable.
لا، أشعر بالارتياح.